Paula Ramos-Silva, PhD















@ORCII

@MyWebsite

Data analysis, research and education are my biggest passions. My work has strong focus on genes and proteins, from bacteria to animals. In my teaching and research, I integrate multiple approaches ranging from molecular biology to large-scale computational analyses of genomics, transcriptomics and proteomics data. Therefore, I see myself as a combination of an experimental and a computational biologist.

EMPLOYMENT HISTORY

<u>Affiliations</u>: Plankton Diversity and Evolution Group, Naturalis Biodiversity Center & Institute for Biodiversity and Ecosystem Dynamics, University of Amsterdam, The Netherlands

Project: Evolution of planktonic gastropod calcification (EPIC)

Advisor: Dr. Katja Peijnenburg

01/11/2019 - 30/04/2020 Maternity Leave

01/03/2014 - 30/04/2018 **Postdoctoral Researcher**

Affiliation: Computational Genomics Group, Instituto Gulbenkian de

Ciência, Portugal

<u>Project</u>: Understanding the evolutionary history and the diversity of

bacterial endosporulation (EvoSpore)

Advisors: Dr. José Pereira-Leal and Dr. Adriano O. Henriques

09/01/2009 - 19/12/2013 **PhD Candidate**

<u>Affiliations</u>: Computational Science Section, University of Amsterdam, The Netherlands & Biogéosciences, University of

Burgundy, France

<u>Project</u>: Marie Curie ITN Biomineralization: understanding of basic mechanisms for the design of novel strategies in nanobiotechnology

(BIOMINTEC)

Supervisors: Prof. Peter Sloot, Dr. Jaap Kaandorp and Dr. Frédéric

Marin

01/11/2007 - 30/11/2008 Research Analyst

<u>Affiliation</u>: Centre of Biological and Chemical Engineering, Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon, Portugal

EDUCATION

09/01/2009 - 19/12/2013 **PhD in Biology**

Informatics Institute, University of Amsterdam, The Netherlands <u>Thesis</u>: Biocalcification of mollusk shells and coral skeletons. Integrating molecular, proteomics and bioinformatics methods Link

01/09/2001 - 10/10/2007

Integrated MSc (BSc + MSc) in Biological Engineering
Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon, Portugal &
Faculty of Engineering, Lund University, Sweden
Thesis: Removal of 17β-estradiol from water using molecularly imprinted polyethersulfone microspheres Link

PUBLICATIONS

Peer-reviewed articles

- 1. <u>Ramos-Silva P</u>*, Odendaal M-L*, Wall-Palmer D, Mekkes L, Peijnenburg KTCA. Transcriptomic responses of adult versus juvenile atlantids to ocean acidification. Frontiers in Marine Science, 2022; 9:801458. (*co-authors) https://doi.org/10.3389/fmars.2022.801458
- 2. <u>Ramos-Silva P</u>, Wall-Palmer D, Marlétaz F, Marin F, Peijnenburg KTCA. Evolution and biomineralization of pteropod shells. Journal of Structural Biology, 2021; 213(4):107779. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jsb.2021.107779
- 3. Wall-Palmer D, Mekkes L, <u>Ramos-Silva P</u>, Dämmer LK, Goetze E, Bakker K, Duijm E, Peijnenburg, KTCA. The impacts of past, present and future ocean chemistry on predatory planktonic snails. Royal Society Open Science, 2021; 8:202265. https://doi.org/10.1098/rsos.202265
- 4. Choo LQ, Bal TMP, Choquet M, Smolina I, <u>Ramos-Silva P</u>, Marlétaz F, Kopp, M, Hoarau G, Peijnenburg KTCA. Novel genomic resources for shelled pteropods: a draft genome and target capture probes for *Limacina bulimoides*, tested for cross-species relevance. BMC Genomics, 2020; 21(1):11. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12864-019-6372-z
- Ramos-Silva P, Serrano M, Henriques AO. From root to tips: sporulation evolution and specialization in *Bacillus subtilis* and the intestinal pathogen *Clostridioides difficile*.
 Molecular Biology and Evolution, 2019; 36(12):2714-36.
 https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msz175
- 6. Le Roy N, Jackson D, Marie B, <u>Ramos-Silva P</u>, Marin F. The evolution of metazoan alphacarbonic anhydrases and their roles in calcium carbonate biomineralization. Frontiers in Zoology, 2014; 11(1):75. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12983-014-0075-8
- 7. Ramos-Silva P, Kaandorp J, Herbst F, Plasseraud L, Alcaraz G, Stern C, Corneillat M, Guichard N, Durlet C, Luquet G, Marin F. The skeleton of the staghorn coral *Acropora millepora*: molecular and structural characterization. PLoS One, 2014; 9(6):e97454. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0097454
- 8. Marin F, Le Roy N, Marie B, <u>Ramos-Silva P</u>, Bundeleva I, Guichard N, Immel F. Metazoan calcium carbonate biomineralizations: macroevolutionary trends—challenges for the coming decade. Bulletin de la Société Géologique de France, 2014; 185(4):217-32. https://doi.org/10.2113/gssgfbull.185.4.217
- 9. Marie B, <u>Ramos-Silva P</u>, Marin F, Marie A. Proteomics of CaCO₃ biomineral-associated proteins: how to properly address their analysis. Proteomics, 2013; 13(21):3109-16. https://doi.org/10.1002/pmic.201300162
- 10. <u>Ramos-Silva P</u>, Kaandorp J, Huisman L, Marie B, Zanella-Cléon I, Guichard N, Miller DJ, Marin F. The skeletal proteome of the coral Acropora millepora: the evolution of calcification by co-option and domain shuffling. Molecular Biology and Evolution, 2013; 30(9):2099-112. https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/mst109

- 11. Marie B, Jackson DJ, <u>Ramos-Silva P</u>, Zanella-Cléon I, Guichard N, Marin F. The shell-forming proteome of *Lottia gigantea* reveals both deep conservations and lineage-specific novelties. The FEBS Journal, 2013; 280(1):214-32. https://doi.org/10.1111/febs.12062
- 12. <u>Ramos-Silva P</u>, Benhamada S, Le Roy N, Marie B, Guichard N, Zanella-Cléon I, Plasseraud L, Corneillat M, Alcaraz G, Kaandorp J, Marin F. Novel molluskan biomineralization proteins retrieved from proteomics: a case study with Upsalin. ChemBioChem, 2012; 13(7):1067-78. https://doi.org/10.1002/cbic.201100708

Letters and reports

- 13. <u>Ramos-Silva P</u>, Brito PH, Serrano M, Henriques AO, Pereira-Leal JB. Rethinking the niche of upper-atmosphere bacteria: draft genome sequences of *Bacillus aryabhattai* C765 and *Bacillus aerophilus* C772, isolated from rice fields. Genome Announcements, 2015; 3(2): e00094-15. PubMed https://doi.org/10.1128/genomeA.00094-15
- Ramos-Silva P, Marin F, Kaandorp J, Marie B. Biomineralization toolkit: the importance of sample cleaning prior to the characterization of biomineral proteomes. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences USA, 2013; 110(24):E2144-6. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1303657110

Book chapters

- Deutekom ES, Konglerd P, <u>Ramos-Silva P</u>, Kaandorp JA. From Molecules to Morphologies, a Multiscale Modeling Approach to Unravel the Complex System of Coral Calcification. The Cnidaria, Past Present and Future, Springer, 2016; pp 223-36. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-31305-4 14
- 16. <u>Ramos-Silva P</u>, Marin F. Proteins as functional units of biocalcification an overview. Biomineralization: From Fundamentals to Biomaterials and Environmental Issues, Key Engineering Materials, 2016; 672:183-90. https://doi.org/10.4028/www.scientific.net/KEM.672.183
- 17. Le Roy N, Jackson DJ, Marie B, <u>Ramos-Silva P</u>, Marin F. Carbonic anhydrase and metazoan biocalcification: a focus on molluscs. Biomineralization: From Fundamentals to Biomaterials and Environmental Issues, Key Engineering Materials, 2016; 672:151-157. https://doi.org/10.4028/www.scientific.net/KEM.672.151
- 18. Marin F, Le Roy N, Marie B, <u>Ramos-Silva P</u>, Wolf S, Benhamada S, Guichard N, Immel F. Synthesis of Calcium Carbonate Biological Materials: How Many Proteins are Needed? Bioceramics 25, Key Engineering Materials, 2014; 614:52-61. https://doi.org/10.4028/www.scientific.net/KEM.614.52
- 19. Marin F, Marie B, Benhamada S, <u>Ramos-Silva P</u>, Le Roy N, Guichard N, Wolf S, Montagnani C, Joubert C, Piquemal D, Saulnier D, Gueguen Y. 'Shellome': proteins involved in mollusc shell biomineralization diversity, functions. International Symposium on Pearl Research, Terrapub, 2013; pp 149–16. (Link NA)

TEACHING

11/2020-21	Guest lecturer in bioinformatics for the course Biological Oceanography, MSc level, University of Amsterdam, The Netherlands (~4 hours)
11/2020-21	Teaching assistant in laboratory practicals for the course Biological Oceanography, MSc level, University of Amsterdam, The Netherlands (24 hours)
10/2018	Lecturer of the module Computational Biology and Bioinformatics at the Tirana

Mathematical and Computational Biology Workshop, Albania (4 hours)

07/2014-15 Guest lecturer, journal club coordinator and evaluator of final presentations for the course Research in Bioinformatics, MSc level, University of Lisbon, Portugal (10 hours)

01/2014-15 Lecturer of Applied Genetics and Statistics, BSc level, University of the Nouvelle Grand'Anse, Haiti. This teaching was part of a program organized by the NGO Haitian Connection (haitianconnection.org). (140 hours)

SUPERVISION & MENTORING

03/2021 - 06/2022	Gloria Casas Canales
	MSc Freshwater & Marine Biology, University of Amsterdam
	Project: Transcriptomic responses of the sub-Antarctic ptero

Project: Transcriptomic responses of the sub-Antarctic pteropod Limacina

retroversa to ocean acidification: adults vs juveniles

09/2021 - 10/2021 Héloïse Ribot

MSc Science Education and Communication, Utrecht University Project: "Seashells inspire CO₂ storage" - popular science article

05/2020 - 11/2020 Mari-Lee Odendaal

MSc Biology, Wageningen University & Research

Project: Transcriptomic responses of juvenile versus adult shelled

heteropods under decreasing ocean pH

01/2019 - 09/2019 Jack Smith

MSc Biology, Leiden University

Project: Screening for fast-evolving genes in pteropod species

INVITED TALKS & SEMINARS

03/2022	Colloquium Live at Tribune, Naturalis Biodiversity Center, Leiden, The Netherlands
03/2022	Marine Genomics & Evolution Symposium, Naturalis Biodiversity Center, Leiden,
	The Netherlands
07/2019	Meeting: Understanding biomineralisation and the impact of global change in marine
	organisms, Institute for Advanced Study, Amsterdam, The Netherlands
10/2018	Tirana Mathematical and Computational Biology Workshop, Tirana, Albania,
10/2013	Research Seminar, Thomas E. Starzl Transplantation Institute, University of
	Pittsburgh, USA

CONFERENCE TALKS

06/2022	Meeting of the Netherlands Society for Evolutionary Biology, Ede, The Netherlands
03/2022	Ocean Sciences Meeting, Hawaii, virtual
09/2019	15 th International Symposium on Biomineralization, Munich, Germany
04/2019	Poster pitch at The Conference of the Netherlands Society for Evolutionary Biology,
	Ede, The Netherlands
08/2013	12 th International Symposium on Biomineralization, Freiberg, Germany
08/2013	5 th Meeting - COST Action Biomineralix, Bologna, Italy
09/2012	4th Meeting - COST Action Biomineralix, Aarhus, Denmark
02/2011	Biomintec International Workshop - Molecular Biomineralization in Marine
	Organisms: Nanobiotecnology and Biomedical Applications, Palermo, Italy,
06/2010	French Conference on Biology of the Mineralized Tissues (12èmes JFBTM), Saint
	Étienne, France
04/2010	7 th International Symposium on Networks in Bioinformatics (ISNB 2010), Amsterdam,
	The Netherlands

CONFERENCE POSTERS

09/2019	Pearls of Wisdom: synergising leadership and expertise in molluscan genomics, Kavli
	Royal Society Centre, Chicheley Hall, UK
05/2019	NWO Life Congress, Bunnik, The Netherlands
04/2019	Meeting of the Netherlands Society for Evolutionary Biology, Ede, The Netherlands
08/2017	16th Congress of the European Society for Evolutionary Biology, Groningen, The
	Netherlands
12/2010	Euro ISRS symposium, Wageningen, The Netherlands
07/2010	French Conference on Biology, Computer Science and Mathematics (JOBIM
	2010), Montpellier, France

PERSONAL GRANTS

02/2019 Marie Skłodowska-Curie Individual Fellowship

Project: EPIC - Evolution of planktonic gastropod calcification,

Grant No.: 844345

Funding Source: European Commission Amount and duration: 176k €, 2.5 years Host: Naturalis Biodiversity Center

02/2015 Postdoctoral Fellowship

Project: EvoSpore - Understanding the evolutionary history and the diversity of

bacterial endosporulation

Funding Source: Portuguese Foundation for Science and Technology – FCT

Grant No.: SFRH/BPD/103171/2014 Amount and duration: 55k €, 3 years Host: Instituto Gulbenkian de Ciência

AWARDS

01/2019	Malacological Society of London Travel Award, UK (300 £)
05/2017	2 nd Martin Fellowship, Naturalis Biodiversity Center, The Netherlands (2700 €)
10/2016	1 st Martin Fellowship, Naturalis Biodiversity Center, The Netherlands (1300 €)
07/2013	Scholarship from the National Institutes of Health & Howard Hughes Institute for
	the course Frontiers in Stem Cells & Regeneration, USA (2500 \$)

CERTIFICATIONS & TRAINING

In bioinformatics

03/2022	Genome Assembly and Annotation, physalia-courses.org (online)
11/2021	Ecological and Evolutionary Studies on DNA Methylation in Plants and Animals,
	physalia-courses.org (online)

I participated in six intensive courses organized by The Gulbenkian Training Program in Bioinformatics (gtpb.igc.gulbenkian.pt):

04/2018	Analysis of Differential Expression with RNAseq
04/2017	Advanced Biostatistics for Bioinformatics Tool Users using R
03/2017	Population Genetics and Demographic History: model-based approaches
03/2016	NGS Data Analysis, RNAseq, ChIPseq
11/2014	Bioinformatics using Python for Biologists
10/2014	Transcriptome Analysis, Automatic Function Annotation and Data Mining

\sim	. 1	
1	thor	0
U	ther	5

Otherb	
04/2022	Didactical modules 1-3 and 6, Teaching and Learning Centre FNWI, University of
	Amsterdam
11/2020	EMBO Lab Leadership course for Postdocs, embo.org (online)
09/2013	Frontiers in Stem Cells & Regeneration, Marine Biological Laboratory, Woods Hole,
	MA, USA

PEER-REVIEW SERVICES

Scientific Reports, Frontiers in Genetics, Genome Biology and Evolution, Journal of Proteome Research, Plos One, F1000Research

	T 1		\mathbf{r}	EΑ	A .	ГΤ
1			$\boldsymbol{\nu}$	\mathbf{H}	Λ	 ш.
` '	. ,	-	11	1//	٦,	

09/2022	Naturalis Spotlight: 'The amazing shells of sea butterflies' at the museum LiveScience
09/2021	<u>Promotional video</u> of the publication Evolution and biomineralization of pteropod shells
08/2019	"Shell microstructures of planktonic gastropods" in the Bulletin of The Malacological Society of London Nr 73, The Malacologist (ISSN 1759-1406)
2014-17	Science communication at the annual NOS Alive Music Festival with microscope demonstrations and one-on-one speed dates about what is computational biology, bioinformatics, genes and evolution, Lisbon, Portugal
10/2016	Open Day at the Instituto Gulbenkian de Ciência - I participated in this event by creating an interactive game introducing evolutionary thinking to children and teenagers named "How are animals related?", Oeiras, Portugal
01/2015	Presenting 'A mobility experience' to share my experience living and working abroad as a scientist to the students of the University of Trás-os-Montes and Alto Douro (UTAD), during the EURAXESS Roadshow in Vila Real, Portugal
09/2012	Radio interview "Portuguese in the World", Antena 1 to share my experience abroad and explain my research in biomineralization, Amsterdam, The Netherlands

ACADEMIC SERVICES

2021-22	Manager of the high memory server for the Plankton Diversity and Evolution group at
	Naturalis. Tasks: bridge between researchers and IT unit, maintain system up to date,
	write documentation install/update software, manage user accounts, technical support
	to users

- 2017-18 Manager of the high memory server from the Computational Genomics Laboratory at Instituto Gulbenkian de Ciência. Tasks: maintain system up to date, install software, manage user accounts, technical support to users
- 2014-15 Postdoc Committee member, Instituto Gulbenkian de Ciência, Portugal Main roles:
 - o Organizer of the monthly Careers in Science Seminar Series.
 - Organizer of 2nd Annual Joint Postdoctoral Meeting, Setúbal, Portugal, November 4-6, 2015 with approx. 100 participants
 - o Postdoc representative for different organizations

LANGUAGES

Portuguese (native), English (full - C2*), French (full – C2*), Dutch (limited – B1*) * Levels according to the Common European Framework of Reference